  <chapter id="chapt:uset-documentation">
    <title>User Documentation</title>
  
    <para>
      This chapter deals with writing user documentation, like user guides.
      It gives pointers, and ideas on how it can be done, and shows how
      the CDK documentation is written.
    </para>
    
    <section id="sect:jedit">
      <title>jEdit: a XML aware editor</title>
      
      <para>
        No, <ulink url="http://www.jedit.org/">jEdit</ulink>
	is not the only XML aware editor, and you do not need to use it;
	use any editor you like. It is just mentioned here to show the power
	of an XML aware editor. Emacs can do similar things.
      </para>
      <para>
        What has an XML aware editor to offer over other editors?
	jEdit is a text editor, not a wysiwyg editor, so has some downside
	for Word users. But, for people used to LaTeX or HTML source code,
	jEdit (using a few plugins) offers much functionality like tag completion,
	validation and a structure browser. And regular expression searches,
	XPath searching if you like, XML indentation, and maybe more. But this
	is what I mostly use. Moreover, jEdit is written in Java (which you already
	have installed, because you need it for CDK anyway, and thus runs on your
	favorite platform. And, last but not least, it's a great Java source code
	editor too.
      </para>
      <para>
        So, where do I go to download jEdit?
	<ulink url="http://www.jedit.org/index.php?page=download">jEdit's
	download site</ulink> has binary and installers for most common
	platforms. When this section was written, version 4.1 was the stable
	release.
      </para>
      <para>
        Then remains the question on plugins. jEdit has a very powerful 
	plugin platform (yes, much better than CDK's...). Plugins can be installed
	directly form the internet from within jEdit using an internet connection.
	A separate website, 
	<ulink url="http://plugins.jedit.org/">http://plugins.jedit.org/</ulink>
	is home to those plugins, and many are available.
	The XML specific plugins which I have installed are: 
	<ulink url="http://plugins.jedit.org/plugins/?XML">XML</ulink>, 
	<ulink url="http://plugins.jedit.org/plugins/?XmlIndenter">XmlIndenter</ulink> and
	<ulink url="http://plugins.jedit.org/plugins/?SideKick">SideKick</ulink>.
	The first contains the tag completion, and tag insertion (based on DTD or 
	XML Schema), and the second... well, that must be clear.
	The last plugin offers a Structure Browser which shows the XML structure in
	tree format. Very useful.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="sect:classes.mod">
      <title>CDK's XML URL module thingy</title>
      
      <para>
        This XML entity module can be included in your XML file, and then offers
	entities (kind of macro's) that provide a DocBook ulink element pointing
	to the JavaDoc documentation of the CDK classes on the CDK website.
      </para>
      <para>
        For example, the module provides the <emphasis>org.Atom</emphasis> entity of which
	the value is &lt;ulink url="http://cdk.sf.net/api/org/openscience/cdk/Atom.html">Atom&lt;/ulink>.
	The <filename>classes.mod</filename> file is generated using a JavaDoc doclet,
	in the <filename role="directory">cdk/doc/javadoc</filename> directory.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="sect:cdk-tutorial">
      <title>CDK Programming Tutorial</title>

      <para>There is a sort of CDK Programming Tutorial online. It is
        written in DocBook XML 4.1.2 (like most of our documentation).</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="sect:jcp-userGuide">
      <title>Example: JChemPaint User Guide</title>
      <para>
        An example of user documentation is the 
	<ulink url="http://jchempaint.sourceforge.net/userguide.html">User Guide of JChemPaint</ulink>.
	Like the CDK documentation, it is written in DocBook XML. It is
	converted into HTML so that it can be displayed from within the 
	JChemPaint program using Java's standard HTML viewer. Additionally,
	the DocBook source is included in the website source which is
	written in the Website DTD, written by Norman Walsh, who is also one
	of the main developers of DocBook XML. The Website DTD was designed,
	and extends, the DocBook DTD, and the result is a very nicely 
	integrated user guide pages.
      </para>
    </section>
    
  </chapter>
