<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "file:/z:/documents/config/xml/dtd/docbookx/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<book>
  <bookinfo> 
	 <title>The Chemistry Development Kit (CDK)</title> 
	 <subtitle>A Java library for Computational Chemistry and Chemoinformatics</subtitle> 
	 <author> 
		<authorblurb> 
		  <para> The author is Assistant Professor of Chemistry at the
			 <ulink url="http://www.nd.edu/~gezelter/">Chemoinformatics
				Workgroup</ulink> @ 
			 <ulink url="http://www.nd.edu">University of Notre Dan</ulink> Notre Dame, IN, USA.</para> 
		</authorblurb> 
		<firstname>Dan</firstname> 
		<surname>Gezelter</surname> 
	 </author>
	 <author> 
		<authorblurb> 
		  <para> The author is head of the 
			 <ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de/departments/ChemInf">Chemoinformatics
				Workgroup</ulink> @ 
			 <ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de">The Max Planck Institute of
				Chemical Ecology</ulink> in Jena, Germany. He enjoys running, cooking, eating
			 and classic as well as all kinds of other well made music. He plays flute and
			 piano. </para> 
		</authorblurb> 
		<firstname>Christoph</firstname> 
		<surname>Steinbeck</surname> 
	 </author> 
	 <author> 
		<authorblurb> 
		  <para> The author is a student of chemistry at the 
			 <ulink url="http://www.kun.nl/">University of Nijmegen</ulink> in the Netherlands 
		  </para> 
		</authorblurb> 
		<firstname>Egon</firstname> 
		<surname>Willighagen</surname> 
	 </author> 
	 <affiliation> 
		<orgname>Max Planck Institute of Chemical Ecology</orgname> 
		<address><street>Carl-Zeiss-Promenade
		  10</street><postcode>D-07745</postcode><city>Jena</city><email>steinbeck@ice.mpg.de</email><phone>+49(0)3641-643644</phone><fax>+49(0)3641-643665</fax><country>Germany</country></address>
		
	 </affiliation>
	 
	 <copyright> 
		<year>2000</year> 
		<holder>The CDK project</holder> 
	 </copyright> 
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter> 
	 <title>What is the CDK?</title> 
	 <para>
The CDK classes are Java utitility classes for ChemoInformatics and Computational chemistry, written in Java. They are developed constantly developed parallel
to other projects that make use of them.
They are a complete re-write of the CompChem classes that were the basis of <ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/JChemPaint">JChemPaint</ulink>, a Java Editor 
for 2D chemical structures, and of <ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/JMDraw">JMDraw</ulink>, a Java package for the graphical layout of 2D chemical structures 
	</para>

	<para>
A re-write was needed to in order to assure the widest possible usability. It is also intended to port
<ulink url="http://www.openscience.org/jmol">JMol</ulink>, a 3D molecular visualization tool, to the CDK.	
	</para>
	<para>		
		The CDK classes support (or will support, as soon as ported from the old CompChem library): 
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Classes for Atoms, Molecules and other chemical concepts.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Utilities for importing and exporting chemical structures (Molecules or arrays of Atoms) using standard chemical files format.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Utility classes for handling chemical elements and isotopes.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A class that parses a molecular formula (a String of characters) and returns an array of Nodes.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					An isomorphisms tester that compares to structures and returns if they are isomorph. I'm almost sure, that the implementation is not strictly valid, but it 
					seems to work
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A SMILES parser (hidden as a static method in compchem.ChemFileUtils), which so far only implements the SSMILES standard.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					An implementation of John Figueras, "Ring Perception Using Breadth-First Search", J. Chem. Inf. Comput Sci. 1996, 36, 986-991.
				</para>
			</listitem>
   		</itemizedlist>
	</para> 
	<para>
	Please <ulink url="api/index.html">check the existing API documentation</ulink> for information on which classes are already implemented.
	</para>
  </chapter> 
  <chapter> 
	 <title>Who develops the CDK?</title> 
	 <para>
	  	The CDK is a joint venture of the JMol and JChemPaint developers who would like to see a general-purpose open-source library for 
		computational chemistry and chemoinformatics. Check the developers list on the <ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/CompChem">CDK pages.</ulink>
	</para> 
  </chapter> 
  <chapter> 
	 <title>How is the CDK developed</title> 
	 <para>
	 	The CDK is mantained as a <ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net">SourceForge</ulink> project under
		<ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/CompChem">http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/CompChem</ulink>. 
		Please check the SourceForge site documentation for more.
		SourceForge gives us bugtracking, mailing lists, support manager and last not least CVS access.
	</para> 
  </chapter> 
  <chapter> 
	 <title>How can I participate?</title> 
	 <para>
		Check the <ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net">SourceForge</ulink> site documentation on how to access the CVS.
		If you actively want to contribute, please get a SourceForge accoutn, contact the project admin so that he can
		add you to the developers list
	</para> 
  </chapter> 
  </book>
