<refentry id="cdk-rfc-18">

  <refentryinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>
        <date>2003-07-01</date>
        <authorinitials>elw</authorinitials>
        <revremark>
          See <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=2684528&amp;forum_id=2178">email archive</ulink>.
        </revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </refentryinfo>


  <refnamediv>
    <refname>RFC CDK #18: A revised RFC system</refname>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Replaces</title>
    <para>
      This RFC replaces <ulink url="http://cdk.sf.net/rfc1.html">RFC #1</ulink> 
      (once accepted).
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  
  <refsect1>
    <title>Proposal</title>

    <refsect2>
      <title>The Request For Comment (RFC)</title>
      <para>
 Any change in the API of the CDK should be formalized in aRequest For 
 Comment's (RFC's). A RFC is a document like this which is written by one or 
 more developers, containing a API description, like package names, class 
 organization, method names, etc. etc. RFC's will serve as a discussion 
 platform and as a documentation tool. The RFC may be changed during the 
 period of discussion on the developers mailing list 
 (cdk-devel@li...).
      </para>
    </refsect2>
 
    <refsect2>
      <title>The Call For Votes (CFV)</title>
      <para>
 At any time the writers of the RFC may choose to Call For Votes (CFV). To do 
 so, they compose a final RFC which will be subject to majority voting. When 
 called for votes, each CDK developer and user can vote in favor or against 
 the RFC. The voting period is at least two weeks, and at most three weeks, 
 and will take place by using voting ballots that are send along with the CFV.
 During July and August the minimum number of weeks for the voting period.
 The writer is strongly encouraged to send a reminder email a few days before
 the end of the voting period.
      </para>
      
      <para>
 Filled in CFVs are returned by email to the developers mailing list, and are 
 preferably signed with a PGP/GnuPG key known by free keyservers. One can only 
 vote in favor (YES) or against (NO) the acceptance of a RFC, and the majority 
 of votes count.
      </para>
 
      <para>
 A RFC is only valid if it includes this information:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>A name. This is normally a sentence describing its intend.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>A "Proposal" paragraph. This will describe the may, should, and must's
        which the RFC will enforce whence it is accepted.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>A "Reason" paragraph. This will describe why the RFC is needed, and may
        include arguments to convince developers and users to accept the RFC.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>A list of accepted RFCs that it will replace.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
 The voting ballot must resemble the following format, and must include all 
 information and fields found in the following example ballot:
<literallayout>
 =============================================================
  Name:
  Email:
  PGP/GPG key:
 
  I vote
 
  [ ] YES
  [ ] NO
 
  on the acceptance of RFC #2 posted on 22 May 2002 with the
  title "list of core classes". The content of this RFC can be
  found at http://cdk.sourceforge.net/rfc2.html.
 =============================================================
</literallayout>
       </para>

       <para>
 The proper RFC number and title must be given as well as a link to the final 
 RFC and the date on which the final RFC was sent to the developers mailing 
 list. 
 </para>
 </refsect2>
 
   <refsect2>
     <title>Counting Votes</title>
     <para>
 After the voting period is over, and the CFV is closed, the votes in favor and
 the votes against are both counted. At least a total of three votes are
 required to resolve a CFV. If less than three people vote on a CFV, then
 the RFC is *not* accepted, even if all votes are in favor of the RFC.
 The RFC is accepted if the majority of votes is in favor of the RFC. If the
 majority of votes is against the RFC, then the RFC is not accepted. In case
 of equal numbers, the RFC is not accepted either. After, and if, the RFC is
 accepted, the RFC will be valid until replaced by another accepted RFC.
      </para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Reason</title>
    <para>
<ulink url="http://cdk.sf.net/rfc1.html">RFC #1</ulink> did not put a limit on the minimum amount of days the voting period 
 must take. This, amongst possible other factors, leaded to a situation where 
 only one person voted on the CFVs #14 and #16. This RFC adds a minimal amount
 of weeks, adds a minimum number of total votes before the RFC can be accepted
 at all, and adds a advisory to send an email to remind people of the CFV a few
 days before the end of the voting period.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Proposers</title>
    <para>
      Egon Willighagen, Christoph Steinbeck
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  
</refentry>
