<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.5.0//EN" 
                         "../website-2.5.0/schema/dtd/website.dtd" [
]>
<webpage id="introduction">
  <config param="last-change-by" value="$Author$"/>
  <config param="rcsdate" value="$Date$"/>

  <head>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <titleabbrev>Introduction</titleabbrev>
    <summary>Information about the CDK project.</summary>
  </head>

	<section>
		<title>About the Chemistry Development Kit</title>
		<para>
			The CDK project was started in September 2000 to replace the CompChem libraries used by
			JChemPaint, Jmol and SENECA. It no longer is in its initial stage, but is slowly getting a solid
			state. The people involved in setting up the project are
			<ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de/~stein">Christoph Steinbeck</ulink>
			then at the
			<ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de/departments/cheminf">Chemoinformatics Group</ulink> at the
			<ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de">Max Planck Institute of Chemical Ecology in Jena</ulink>,
			as well as <ulink url="mailto:egonw@sci.kun.nl">Egon Willighagen</ulink> from the 
            <ulink url="http://www.kun.nl/">University of Nijmegen, The Netherlands</ulink>,
			who is also involved with JChemPaint and many other Java Chemoinformatics programs, and
			<ulink url="mailto:gezelter@maul.chem.nd.edu">Dan Gezelter</ulink> from 
            <ulink url="http://www.nd.edu/">Notre Dame University, South Bend, USA</ulink>, 
            the initiator of Jmol, a 3D viewer and analyzer for molecules .
		</para>
		<para>
			Now, the rewrite of these CompChem/CDK library classes do somehow effect
			all of our projects.
			All of our code relies to some extend on the so-called CompChem classes
			for computational chemistry. Christoph Steinbeck started this chemistry library when 
            he started programming SENECA, a system for Computer Assisted Structure Elucidation.
			It turned out that some of
			the code had design flaws that prevented others, like the authors of
			(<ulink url="http://www.jmol.org/">Jmol</ulink>) to use it.
			Egon, Dan and Chris now met in September 2000 at the University of Notre Dame,
			South Bend, Chicago, and redesigned the CompChem classes, calling the
			new project the "Chemistry Development Kit, CDK".
		</para>
		<para>
			Of course, at Notre Dame we were not able to do all the implementations.
			We decided to take some more care this time and start with UML. There
			were UML diagrams created which were later converted to ArgoUML diagrams.
			ArgoUML is Java and can also be used under Windows. UML is hardly used at this
            moment.
		</para>
		<para>
			In the past four years, the CDK library evolved enormously. A CDK based
            JChemPaint version was released in spring 2004, but though initial progress
            was made to port Jmol to CDK, this has been abandoned about a year ago
            for performance reasons. Nevertheless, integration with CDK is progressing.
            In addition to this, three other programs
            are developed that are based on CDK. You can learn about these on the
            page "Software using CDK" (see menu on the left).
		</para>
        <para>
            More information about using CDK can be found in the 
            <ulink url="documentation.html">Documentation</ulink> section
            of this website. People interested in the CDK development are encouraged
            to check out the <ulink url="development.html">Development</ulink> 
            section as well. If you have questions about
            CDK (any question), please see the Contact section for information on how
            to reach the CDK developers.
        </para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Contributors</title>
		<para>
          The list of source code contributors is long and can be viewed from
          <ulink url="contributors.html">the list of contributors</ulink>.
        </para>
    </section>
</webpage>
