<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.0b1//EN" "dtd/website.dtd">
<webpage id="introduction">
  <config param="last-change-by" value="$Author$"/>
  <config param="rcsdate" value="$Date$"/>

  <head>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <titleabbrev>Introduction</titleabbrev>
    <summary>Information about the CDK project.</summary>
  </head>

	<section>
		<title>About this website</title>
		<para>
			The CDK project was started in September 2000 to replace the CompChem libraries used by
			JChemPaint, Jmol and SENECA. It no longer is in its initial stage, but is slowly getting a solid
			state. The people involved are
			<ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de/~stein">Christoph Steinbeck</ulink>
			and his			
			<ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de/departments/cheminf">Chemoinformatics Group</ulink> at the
			<ulink url="http://www.ice.mpg.de">Max Planck Institute of Chemical Ecology in Jena</ulink>,
			as well as <ulink url="mailto:egonw@sci.kun.nl">Egon Willighagen</ulink> from the University of Nijmegen,
			who is also involved with JChemPaint and many other Java Chemoinformatics programs, and
			<ulink url="mailto:gezelter@maul.chem.nd.edu">Dan Gezelter</ulink>, the initiator of Jmol, a 3D viewer and analyzer for molecules .
		</para>
		<para>
			Now, the rewrite of these CompChem/CDK library classes do somehow effect
			all of our projects.
			All of our code relies to some extend on the so-called CompChem classes
			for computational chemistry. Christoph Steinbeck started this chemistry library when he started programming SENECA, a system for Computer Assisted Structure Elucidation.
			It turned out that some of
			the code had design flaws that prevented others, like the authors of
			(<ulink url="http://www.jmol.org/">Jmol</ulink>) to use it.
			Egon, Dan and Chris now met in September 2000 at the University of Notre Dame,
			South Bend, Chicago, and redesigned the CompChem classes, calling the
			new project the "Chemistry Development Kit, CDK".
		</para>
		<para>
			Of course, at Notre Dame we were not able to do all the implementations.
			We decided to take some more care this time and start with UML. There
			are some UML diagrams on the CVS at
			http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/cdk which can be views with the
			program Linux program dia. Egon has moved them to ArgoUML,
			which is Java and can also be used under Windows.
		</para>
		<para>
			In the past two years, the CDK library evolved enormously. In the end of this
            year JChemPaint will have a first stable release based on CDK, and Jmol will
            follow somewhere in Janury 2003. In addition to this, three other programs
            are developed that are based on CDK. You can learn about these on the
            page "Software using CDK" (see menu on the left).
		</para>
        <para>
            More information about using CDK can be found in the Documentation section
            of this website. People interested in the CDK development are encouraged
            to check out the Development section as well. If you have questions about
            CDK (any question), please see the Contact section for information on how
            to reach the CDK developers.
        </para>
	</section>

</webpage>
