<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.5.0//EN" 
                         "../website-2.5.0/schema/dtd/website.dtd" [
]>
<webpage id="qualitycontrol">
  <config param="last-change-by" value="$Author$"/>
  <config param="rcsdate" value="$Date$"/>

  <head>
    <title>Quality Control</title>
    <titleabbrev>Quality Control</titleabbrev>
    <summary>Description on how the CDK project tries to keep top quality
       algorithm implementations and source code.</summary>
  </head>

  <para>
    This page describes how the CDK Project tries to maintain the
    quality of both the source code as well as the implemented algorithms.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The results of tests described below are found in the left menu.
  </para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Algorithm Quality</title>
    <para>
      The quality of the algorithms is measured using JUnit testing. These
      tests check wether the classes in the library perform as they are expected.
      This means both that the data classes act as expected, but also that
      algorithms function as expected. It's important to repeat these tests
      over and over again to be able to maintain the source code (in terms of
      API changes, relayout, faster algorithm implementation, etc).
    </para>
    <para>
      Currently, the results of the JUnit tests are not online, but with the
      Ant <filename>build.xml</filename> script these can be reproduced with
      the <command>test-all</command> target.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Source code Quality</title>
    <para>
      At this moment, the quality of the source code is measured using PMD
      and the use of JavaDoc. The first checks for many common and less common
      coding mistakes, like empty if-blocks, empty try-blocks and unused
      variables. The JavaDoc test results show how well the classes are
      documented, and this is, ofcourse, of major importance to program
      developers who would like to use the CDK library.
    </para>
  </section>

  
</webpage>
