<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.5.0//EN" 
                         "../website-2.5.0/schema/dtd/website.dtd" [
]>
<webpage id="software">
  <config param="last-change-by" value="$Author$"/>
  <config param="rcsdate" value="$Date$"/>

  <head>
    <title>Software using CDK</title>
    <titleabbrev>Software using CDK</titleabbrev>
    <summary>This page contains a list of programs that use
      (partly) CDK.</summary>
  </head>

  <section>
    <title>Software using CDK</title>

    <para>
      This page contains a list of programs that use CDK to some extent.
      If your software uses CDK and is missing from this list, please send
      an email to <ulink url="mailto:cdk-devel@lists.sf.net">cdk-devel@lists.sf.net</ulink>.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>HyperDossier</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.intellidos.com/products/hyperdossier.htm">Intellidos HyperDossier</ulink>
        is a light weight web application that collates and
        cross links scientific data. All the latest information about a particular
        scientific entity, from a variety of sources may be collated into a single
        electronic dossier. Hyperlinking between these dossiers creates a web of
        scientific information that may be readily browsed by scientists.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JChemPaint</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://jchempaint.sf.net/">JChemPaint</ulink> is a 2D chemical diagram
        editor like many others and is fully based on CDK.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Jmol</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.jmol.org/">Jmol</ulink> is a 3D chemical 
        animator/viewer. Version 6 to and including 9 use the cdk-core classes 
        for data storage. Later, in the 10 preseries, more efficient Java classes 
        were implemented to allow beter rendering performance.
        A tight integration with CDK is possible: CDK plugins and IO can be used
        and the renderer can be used by CDK based software.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JOELib</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://joelib.sf.net">JOELib</ulink> is a chemical library like
	CDK itself and is based on the OELib library written in C++. It's licenced
	GPL, and uses an customized versino of CDK's CML library for reading CML.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Jumbo</title>
      <para>
        Jumbo is software aiming at converting full chemical documents (in any format)
        into Chemical Markup Language, applying chemical perception and conversion
        in the process if needed.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>NMRShiftDB</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.nmrshiftdb.org/">NMRShiftDB</ulink>
        is an open-source, open-content database of organic structures and
        their NMR data.
        <ulink url="http://cdk.sf.net/biblio.html#ste2002">[STE2002]</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Nomen</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://chemnomparse.sf.net/">Nomen</ulink> is a IUPAC name
        parser being developed at the University of Manchester, UK.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>SafeBase(TM)</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.therastrat.com/">SafeBase (TM)</ulink>
        is a theragenomics knowledge management
        system on adverse drug reactions developed by
        <ulink url="http://www.therastrat.com/">TheraSTrat</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>SENECA</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://seneca.sf.net/">SENECA</ulink>
        is a software package for Computer-Assisted Structure Elucidation (CASE) of 
        organic molecules based on spectroscopic data
        <ulink url="http://cdk.sf.net/biblio.html#ste2001">[STE2001]</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>QueryConstructor</title>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.intellidos.com/products/queryconstructor.htm">Intellidos QueryConstructor</ulink>
        is an ad hoc cross-domain query tool that allows
        scientists with no knowledge of SQL to build complex queries on complex
        scientific data.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>XB Edit (Working title)</title>
      <para>
        XB Edit is an Extreme Blue (tm) internship project currently
        in progress at IBM Germany Development Lab in Boeblingen near Stuttgart, Germany.
        XB Edit is supposed grow into a combined 2D/3D editor for chemical structure and
        uses the CDK for handling the standard chemoinformatical algorithms.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

</webpage>
